What if I could present you a story
ماذا لو كان بامكاني أن أقدم لكم قصة
that you would remember with your entire body
حيث سيكون بمقدوركم تذكرها بكامل حواسكم
and not just with your mind?
وليس فقط بعقلكم؟
My whole life as a journalist, I've really been compelled
على مدى حياتي كصحفية، كنت مجبرة على
to try to make stories that can make a difference
نقل وكتابة قصص يمكنها إحداث فرق
and maybe inspire people to care.
وربما إلهام الناس لإبداء الإهتمام.
I've worked in print. I've worked in documentary.
عملت في الطباعة، وعملت في قسم التوثيق،
I've worked in broadcast.
وعملت في قسم البث.
But it really wasn't until I got involved with virtual reality
ولكن في الحقيقة لم يكن كذلك إلى أن تورطت في الواقع الافتراضي
that I started seeing these really intense,
حيث بدأت أرى ردات فعل الناس المنفعلة جدًا،
authentic reactions from people
والصادقة.
that really blew my mind.
والتي أفقدتني صوابي.
So the deal is that with VR, virtual reality,
اذا، الاتفاق هو أنه عن طريق الواقع الافتراضي
I can put you on scene
سيكون بمقدوري وضعكم في موقع الحدث
in the middle of the story.
كجزء من القصة.
By putting on these goggles that track wherever you look,
عن طريق لبس هذه النظارات والتي تلاحقك أينما تنظر،
you get this whole-body sensation,
ستحظى بهذا الاحساس على كامل جسدك،
like you're actually, like, there.
وكأنك في الواقع متواجد هناك.
So five years ago was about when I really began to push the envelope
لذا قبل خمس سنوات، بدأت اذهب بعيدًا
with using virtual reality and journalism together.
في استخدام الواقع الافتراضي جنبًا إلى جنب مع الصحافة.
And I wanted to do a piece about hunger.
وأردت كتابة قصة تتعلق بالجوع.
Families in America are going hungry, food banks are overwhelmed,
تعاني الأسر في أميركا من الجوع، وبنوك الطعام تنوء،
and they're often running out of food.
وغالبًا ما ينفد مالديهم من مواد غذائية.
Now, I knew I couldn't make people feel hungry,
الآن، كنت أعرف أنه ليس بمقدوري حمل الناس على الشعور بالجوع،
but maybe I could figure out a way to get them to feel something physical.
ولكن ربما بوسعي اكتشاف طريقة تجعلهم يشعرون بشيء فيزيائي.
So -- again, this is five years ago --
لذلك، مرة أخرى، كان هذا قبل خمس سنوات--
so doing journalism and virtual reality together
حيث أن العمل على الواقع الإفتراضي والصحافة معًا
was considered a worse-than-half-baked idea,
كان يعتبر أكثر من مجرد فكرة غير واقعية،
and I had no funding.
وكنت أفتقر إلى التمويل.
Believe me, I had a lot of colleagues laughing at me.
صدقوني، كان العديد من زملائي في العمل يضحكون على.
And I did, though, have a really great intern,
وقد قمت بذلك، بصحبة متدربة رائعة جدًا،
a woman named Michaela Kobsa-Mark.
امرأة تدعى ميشيلا كوبسا-مارك.
And together we went out to food banks
وذهبنا معًا إلى بنوك الطعام
and started recording audio and photographs.
وبدأنا بأخذ تسجيلات صوتية وإلتقاط الصور.
Until one day she came back to my office
حتى عادت إلى مكتبي ذات يوم
and she was bawling, she was just crying.
وهي تصيح وتبكي.
She had been on scene at a long line,
كانت حاضرة على مشهد أثناء وقوفها في صف طويل،
where the woman running the line was feeling extremely overwhelmed,
حيث كانت المرأة التي تنظم الصف مغلوبة على أمرها بشدة،
and she was screaming, "There's too many people!
وكانت تصيح، "يوجد عدد كبير من الناس!
There's too many people!"
يوجد عدد كبير من الناس!"
And this man with diabetes doesn't get food in time,
وهذا الرجل المصاب بالسكري لم يحصل على طعامه في الوقت المحدد،
his blood sugar drops too low, and he collapses into a coma.
فانخفض معدل السكر في دمه بشدة، وسقط بعدها في غيبوبة.
As soon as I heard that audio,
بمجرد أن سمعت هذا التسجيل،
I knew that this would be the kind of evocative piece
عرفت أن هذه ستكون القطعة المثيرة للعواطف
that could really describe what was going on at food banks.
والتي ستصف ما يحدث حقا في بنوك الطعام.
So here's the real line. You can see how long it was, right?
هاهو ذا الصف الحقيقي. يمكنكم أن تروا كم كان طويلًا، أليس كذلك؟
And again, as I said, we didn't have very much funding,
ومجددًا، كما قلت، لم نكن نمتلك الكثير من التمويل،
so I had to reproduce it with virtual humans that were donated,
لذلك توجب على إعادة انتاجه بمساعدة أشخاص افتراضيين بفضل الذي تبرعوا بالمال،
and people begged and borrowed favors to help me create the models
وأولئك الذي توسلوا للحصول عليه واقترضوا حتى أتمكن من إنشاء النماذج
and make things as accurate as we could.
وجعل الأمور دقيقة قدر ما نستطيع.
And then we tried to convey what happened that day
بعدها حاولنا نقل ما حدث ذلك اليوم
with as much as accuracy as is possible.
بأكبر قدر ممكن من الدقة.
(Video) Voice: There's too many people! There's too many people!
(فيديو) صوت: يوجد العديد من الناس! يوجد العديد من الناس!
Voice: OK, he's having a seizure.
صوت: حسنًا، إنه يتشنج.
Voice: We need an ambulance.
صوت: نحن بحاجة إلى عربة اسعاف.
Nonny de la Peña: So the man on the right,
نوني دو لا بينا: اذاً الرجل على اليمين،
for him, he's walking around the body.
بالنسبة له، فهو يحوم حول الجسد.
For him, he's in the room with that body.
بالنسبة له، هو موجود في الغرفة مع ذلك الجسد.
Like, that guy is at his feet.
مثل، ذلك الفتى الجاثي على قدميه.
And even though, through his peripheral vision,
وعلى الرغم من أنه من خلال الرؤية المحيطية،
he can see that he's in this lab space,
يمكنه أن يرى أنه موجود في المعمل،
he should be able to see that he's not actually on the street,
يجب أن يكون قادرا أن يدرك أنه ليس موجود في الشارع،
but he feels like he's there with those people.
ولكنه يشعر وكأنه موجود هناك مع هؤلاء الناس.
He's very cautious not to step on this guy
يبدو حذرًا جدًا كي لا يطأ على هذا الشخص
who isn't really there, right?
الغير موجود أصلًا، أليس كذلك؟
So that piece ended up going to Sundance in 2012,
انتهى الأمر بوصول هذه القطعة إلى سندانس في العام 2012،
a kind of amazing thing, and it was the first virtual reality film
شيء مدهش نوعًا ما، وقد كانت أساسًا أول فيلم واقع افتراضي
ever, basically.
على الإطلاق.
And when we went, I was really terrified.
وعندما ذهبنا إلى هناك، كنت مذعورة حقًا.
I didn't really know how people were going to react
لم أكن أدرك حقًا كيف ستكون ردة فعل الناس
and what was going to happen.
وما الذي سيحدث.
And we showed up with this duct-taped pair of goggles.
ولقد عرضناه مع هذا الزوج من النظارت بالشريط اللاصق.
(Video) Oh, you're crying. You're crying. Gina, you're crying.
(فيديو) أوه! أنت تبكين. أنت تبكين. جينا. أنت تبكين.
So you can hear the surprise in my voice, right?
يمكنكم أن تسمعوا نبرة الدهشة في صوتي، أليس كذلك؟
And this kind of reaction ended up being the kind of reaction we saw
وانتهى الأمر بهذا النوع من ردود الفعل الذي رأيناه
over and over and over:
مرارًا وتكرارا.
people down on the ground trying to comfort the seizure victim,
يجثوا البعض على الأرض محاولين التخفيف ألام النوبة على الضحية،
trying to whisper something into his ear
ومحاولين الهمس بشيئ ما في أذنه
or in some way help, even though they couldn't.
أو بطريقة أخرى تقديم المساعدة، على الرغم من عدم تمكنهم من ذلك.
And I had a lot of people come out of that piece saying,
ولقد سمعت العديد من الناس بعد مشاهدة تلك القطعة يقولون،
"Oh my God, I was so frustrated. I couldn't help the guy,"
"يا إلهي، كنت محبطًا جدًا. لم أستطع مساعدة الرجل"
and take that back into their lives.
وتصوروا الأمر في حياتهم الخاصة.
So after this piece was made,
لذلك، بعد عمل هذه القطعة،
the dean of the cinema school at USC, the University of Southern California,
حضر عميد مدرسة السينما في جامعة جنوبي كاليفورنيا،
brought in the head of the World Economic Forum to try "Hunger,"
على رأس المنتدى الاقتصادي العالمي لكي يجرب "الجوع"
and he took off the goggles,
ثم خلع النظارات،
and he commissioned a piece about Syria on the spot.
وفوَّض بعمل قطعة حول سوريا في الحال.
And I really wanted to do something about Syrian refugee kids,
ولقد كنت أود فعلًا القيام بشيء لصالح أطفال اللاجئين السوريين،
because children have been the worst affected by the Syrian civil war.
لأن الأطفال ظلوا أشد المتأثرين بالحرب المدنية السورية.
I sent a team to the border of Iraq to record material at refugee camps,
أرسلت فريقا إلى حدود العراق بغرض تسجيل مادة في مخيمات اللاجئين،
basically an area I wouldn't send a team now,
منطقة ما كنت لأرسل إليها فريقا الآن أساسًا،
as that's where ISIS is really operating.
وذلك حيث يعمل بالضبط تنظيم الدولة الإسلامية.
And then we also recreated a street scene
ومن ثم أعدنا خلق مشهد من الشارع
in which a young girl is singing and a bomb goes off.
حيث تظهر فتاة وهي تغني وفجأة تنطلق القذائف.
Now, when you're in the middle of that scene
الآن، عندما تكون في منتصف ذلك المشهد
and you hear those sounds,
وتسمع هذه الأصوات،
and you see the injured around you,
وترى الإصابات من حولك،
it's an incredibly scary and real feeling.
فهو شيئ مخيف بشكل لا يصدق وإحساس حقيقي.
I've had individuals who have been involved in real bombings tell me
أخبرني أفراد شهدوا تفجيرات حقيقية
that it evokes the same kind of fear.
أنه يثير نفس نوع الخوف.
[The civil war in Syria may seem far away]
[قد تبدو الحرب في سوريا بعيدة جدًا]
[until you experience it yourself.]
[إلى أن تختبرها بنفسك]
(Girl singing)
(فتاة تغني)
(Explosion)
(انفجار)
[Project Syria]
[مشروع سوريا]
[A virtual reality experience]
[تجربة واقع افتراضي]
NP: We were then invited to take the piece
نوني: بعدها تمت دعوتنا لعرض القطعة
to the Victoria and Albert Museum in London.
في متحف فيكتوريا وألبرت في مدينة لندن.
And it wasn't advertised.
ولكن لم يتم عرضها.
And we were put in this tapestry room.
وتم وضعنا في غرفة النسيج هذه.
There was no press about it,
لم تكن هناك تغطية صحفية،
so anybody who happened to walk into the museum to visit it that day
لذلك فإن كل من صادف قدومه إلى المتحف ذلك اليوم
would see us with these crazy lights.
كان يجدنا محاطين بهذه الأضواء المجنونة.
You know, maybe they would want to see the old storytelling of the tapestries.
أتدرون، ربما أرادوا أن يتعرفوا على القصص القديمة المتعلقة بالمفروشات.
They were confronted by our virtual reality cameras.
ولكنهم قوبلوا بكاميرات الواقع الإفتراضي خاصتنا.
But a lot of people tried it, and over a five-day run
ولكن قام العديد من الناس بتجربتها، وخلال 5 أيام من العمل
we ended up with 54 pages of guest book comments,
انتهى الأمر بكتيب من 54 صفحة يضم تعليقات الزوار،
and we were told by the curators there
وقد أخبرنا القائمون على الأمر هناك
that they'd never seen such an outpouring.
أنهم لم يشهدوا مثل هذا التدفق الجماهيري من قبل.
Things like, "It's so real," "Absolutely believable,"
كان لسان حال الناس، "إنه لشيئ حقيقي فعلًا" "قابل للتصديق بكل ما تحمل الكلمة من معنى"
or, of course, the one that I was excited about,
أو، باالتأكيد، التعليق الذي كنت أتوق إليه،
"A real feeling as if you were in the middle of something
"شعور حقيقي كما لو أنك كنت جزءا من شيئ ما
that you normally see on the TV news."
عادة ما تراه في الأخبارعلى شاشة التلفاز."
So, it works, right? This stuff works.
إذا، فإن الأمر ناجح، أليس كذلك؟ هذه الأشياء تنجح.
And it doesn't really matter where you're from or what age you are --
ولا يهم على الإطلاق من أين تنحدر أو كم هو عمرك
it's really evocative.
إنه لشيئ مثير للعواطف حقًا.
Now, don't get me wrong -- I'm not saying that when you're in a piece
الآن، لا تسيئوا فهمي، أنا لا أقول أنه عندما تندمجوا في القطعة
you forget that you're here.
فذلك يعني فقدانكم الإحساس بالمكان.
But it turns out we can feel like we're in two places at once.
ولكن يتضح أنه بمقدورنا الإحساس كما لو أننا نتشارك مكانين في نفس اللحظة.
We can have what I call this duality of presence,
يحدث لنا ما اسميه ثنائية الوجود،
and I think that's what allows me to tap into these feelings of empathy.
وأعتقد أن ذلك هو ما سمح لي بالإستفادة من مشاعر التعاطف هذه.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
So that means, of course,
اذاً، ذلك يعني بكل تأكيد،
that I have to be very cautious about creating these pieces.
أنه يتوجب علي أن أكون حذرة عند صنع هذه القطع.
I have to really follow best journalistic practices
يتوجب على أن أمتثل بشدة لأفضل الممارسات الصحفية
and make sure that these powerful stories
وأن أتأكد من أن هذه القصص المؤثرة
are built with integrity.
تم إنتاجها بنزاهة.
If we don't capture the material ourselves,
إن لم نقم بجمع المواد بأنفسنا،
we have to be extremely exacting
إذاً يتوجب علينا أن نكون دقيقين جدًا
about figuring out the provenance and where did this stuff come from
في ما يتعلق بالمصدر ومن أين جاءت هذه الأشياء
and is it authentic?
وهل هي موثوق بها؟
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أقدم لكم مثالًا.
With this Trayvon Martin case, this is a guy, a kid,
كحالة الصبي ترايفون مارتن هذه،
who was 17 years old and he bought soda and a candy at a store,
وهو صبي يبلغ 17 عامًا، حيث ابتاع مياه غازية وحلوى من المتجر،
and on his way home he was tracked by a neighborhood watchman
وفي طريق عودته إلى المنزل كان يتعقبه حارس الحي
named George Zimmerman who ended up shooting and killing him.
والذي يدعى جورج زميرمان، حيث انتهى الأمر بأن أطلق عليه النار فأرداه قتيلًا.
To make that piece,
من أجل عمل تلك القطعة،
we got the architectural drawings of the entire complex,
حصلنا على رسومات معمارية لكامل المجمَّع،
and we rebuilt the entire scene inside and out, based on those drawings.
ثم أعدنا بناء كامل المشهد من الداخل والخارج، استنادا على هذه الرسومات.
All of the action
تم عمل كل الأحداث
is informed by the real 911 recorded calls to the police.
بناءً على تسجيلات حقيقية لشرطة النجدة.
And interestingly, we broke some news with this story.
وبشكل مثير للإهتمام، تصدرنا نشرات الأخبار بهذه القصة.
The forensic house that did the audio reconstruction, Primeau Productions,
بريمو للإنتاج، وهو بيت الطب الشرعي الذي قام بإعادة تركيب الصوت
they say that they would testify
قالوا أنهم سيشهدون
that George Zimmerman, when he got out of the car,
أن جورج زميرمان سحب زند مسدسه لحظة خروجه من السيارة،
he cocked his gun before he went to give chase to Martin.
قبل أن يشرع في مطاردة مارتن.
So you can see that the basic tenets of journalism,
لذا بامكانكم أن تروا أن المبادئ الأساسية للصحافة،
they don't really change here, right?
لم تتغير بشكل كبير هنا، أليس كذلك؟
We're still following the same principles that we would always.
مازلنا نتبع نفس المبادئ التي ظللنا نتبعها دائما.
What is different is the sense of being on scene,
الشيئ المختلف هو الإحساس بالإنتماء للحدث،
whether you're watching a guy collapse from hunger
في حال ما كنت تشاهد فتى يسقط نتيجة للجوع
or feeling like you're in the middle of a bomb scene.
أو أن تشعر أنك في منتصف مشهد مليءٍ بالقنابل.
And this is kind of what has driven me forward with these pieces,
وهذا هو ما دفعني للأمام بخصوص هذه القطع،
and thinking about how to make them.
والتفكير في كيفية إنتاجها.
We're trying to make this, obviously, beyond the headset, more available.
نحن نحاول أن نجعل الأمر يتعدى مجرد سماعات الرأس.
We're creating mobile pieces like the Trayvon Martin piece.
فنحن نعمل على قطع لأجهزة النقال مثل قطعة ترايفون مارتن.
And these things have had impact.
وهذه الأشياء كان لها تأثير.
I've had Americans tell me that they've donated,
أخبرني أمريكيون أنهم قد تبرعوا،
direct deductions from their bank account, money to go to Syrian children refugees.
من حساباتهم البنكية مباشرة لصالح أطفال اللاجئين السوريين.
And "Hunger in LA," well, it's helped start
وكذلك "الجوع في لوس أنجلوس"، لقد ساعد الأمر
a new form of doing journalism
في بدء شكل جديد من أشكال العمل الصحفي
that I think is going to join all the other normal platforms
والذي أعتقد أنه سيضم كل أنواع المنصات الأخرى المعتادة
in the future.
في المستقبل.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)